Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we have an upper intermediate level lesson.
我是Catherine，今天我们有一节中高级课程。
It's kind of bitter, it's a little bit sad, but it's also kind of sweet.
有点苦涩，有点伤感，但也带着一丝甜蜜。
That's right.
没错。
We have a lesson today all about getting a divorce or divorcing someone.
今天的课程全是关于离婚或与某人离婚的话题。
Yeah.
是啊。
So this is what happens when two people's marriage ends.
这就是两个人婚姻结束时的情景。
They decide they want to leave each other.
他们决定要离开彼此。
They have a divorce.
他们离婚了。
So let's take a listen to today's dialogue and we'll be back in a moment.
那我们先来听听今天的对话，一会儿再回来。
Joanne, let's not make this divorce any more acrimonious than it already is, okay?
Joanne，我们别让这场离婚比现在更激烈了，好吗？
Let's just get down to business and start dividing this stuff up fairly so we can go
我们就直接谈正事，公平地分这些东西，然后各走各的，
our separate ways, all right?
行吗？
Fine with me.
我没意见。
I just want to get this over with.
我只想赶紧把这事了结。
It's important we make a clean break.
重要的是我们要彻底分开。
I should have signed a prenup.
我当初真该签个婚前协议。
What was that?
你说什么？
Nothing.
没什么。
Anyway, you're right.
总之，你说得对。
There's no reason this has to be nasty.
没必要搞得这么难堪。
My lawyer tells me that you've accepted our alimony proposal and the division of property
我的律师告诉我，你已经接受了我们的赡养费方案、财产分割，
as well as the custody agreement.
还有监护权协议。
I keep the cat and you get the dog.
我留猫，你养狗。
So that's done.
那就这么定了。
Finally.
终于。
Well, let's not go there, Joanne.
好了，别扯远了，Joanne。
Okay, so let's start with the record collection.
好吧，那我们从唱片收藏开始分。
I'll take the albums I contributed and you can have your cheesy disco albums back.
我拿我买的那些专辑，你可以拿回你那些俗气的迪斯科唱片。
Fine, but I'm keeping the antique gramophone as my grandfather gave it to me.
行，但我要留着古董留声机，那是我祖父给我的。
I believe that was a wedding present to both of us, Joanne, and you hardly ever use it.
我觉得那是送给咱们俩的结婚礼物，Joanne，而且你几乎从来不用它。
He's my grandfather and he never really liked you anyway.
他是我祖父，反正他从来就没真正喜欢过你。
Whatever.
随便吧。
All right, I'll concede the silly gramophone if you'll agree that I get the silver tea
好吧，如果你同意我拿那套银茶具，我就放弃那个傻留声机。
set.
How typical.
真典型。
When are you ever going to use a silver tea set?
你什么时候会用上银茶具啊？
Fine.
行。
I don't want to drag this out any more than necessary.
我不想把这事拖得比必要的时间更长。
What's next?
接下来是什么？
What about these old photographs?
这些旧照片怎么办？
Which ones?
哪些？
Let me have a look.
让我看看。
Oh, wow, look at that.
哦，哇，看这个。
That brings back memories.
这勾起了回忆。
Remember that?
还记得那个吗？
Our trip to Italy.
我们的意大利之旅。
I remember that day.
我记得那天。
We were going to visit the Trevi Fountain and we got caught in the rain.
我们本来要去参观特雷维喷泉，结果遇上了雨。
And you looked so adorable with your hair all wet.
你头发全湿了的样子可爱极了。
I did take a picture of you standing there in that little alley, smiling and laughing
我确实给你拍了张照片，你站在那个小巷子里，在雨中微笑，
in the rain.
大笑。
Oh, we really did have fun back then, didn't we?
哦，我们那时候真的玩得很开心，对吧？
Oh, Joanne, are we making a big mistake?
哦，Joanne，我们是不是在犯一个大错？
I know our relationship has been on the rocks for some time, but are you sure we can't reconcile
我知道我们的关系已经紧张了一段时间，但你确定我们不能和好，
and try again?
再试一次吗？
I still love you.
我还爱你。
Oh, Jeff, I love you too.
哦，Jeff，我也爱你。
I'm so glad we didn't have to decide who keeps the motorcycle.
我真高兴我们不用决定谁留下摩托车。
The motorcycle?
摩托车？
But that's mine!
但那是我的！
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now, why don't we take a look at six key words on Language Takeaway.
现在，我们来看看“语言要点”中的六个关键词。
Language Takeaway Okay, Marco, this first word is what we call
“语言要点” 好的，Marco，第一个词我们称之为
an SAT word.
SAT词汇。
That means it's very difficult, it's so hard that many high school students in America
意思是它非常难，很多美国高中生在
study it before they go to college.
上大学前都要学它。
Acrimonious.
Acrimonious（激烈的）。
So, the sentence starts off by saying, let's not make this divorce any more acrimonious
句子开头说，“我们别让这场离婚比现在更激烈了”。
than it already is.
This divorce is very acrimonious, but let's not make it worse.
这场离婚已经很激烈了，但我们别让它更糟。
Okay, so acrimonious would be bitter, very complicated.
好的，所以acrimonious就是苦涩、非常复杂的意思。
Hard.
艰难。
So people, emotional about it, you know, people, Joanne and Jeff are getting a divorce.
所以人们情绪激动，你知道，Joanne和Jeff正在离婚。
They're very angry at each other.
他们彼此非常生气。
So they're not having a peaceful divorce.
所以他们不是在和平离婚。
This is the opposite.
这是相反的情况。
It's very bitter, it's very angry.
非常苦涩，非常愤怒。
Can you say this test is very acrimonious?
你能说“这次考试非常激烈”吗？
No.
不。
Usually, relationships are acrimonious.
通常，关系是充满敌意的。
For example, ever since they had that big fight, Jeff and Joanne's relationship has
例如，自从他们大吵一架后，杰夫和乔安妮的关系一直
been very acrimonious.
非常紧张。
Okay, awesome.
好的，太棒了。
So, acrimonious, a very hard word there.
所以，acrimonious，一个很难的词。
As you say, many people study it to pass exams in order to go into college.
正如你所说，很多人为了上大学而学习它来通过考试。
So now you know.
现在你知道了。
Now, moving on, we have a very common legal term.
现在，我们继续，有一个很常见的法律术语。
When people are getting married, they want to sign sometimes a prenup.
当人们结婚时，他们有时想签一份婚前协议。
Yeah, you said it's common.
是的，你说它很常见。
You hear this a lot in movies and TV.
你在电影和电视里经常听到这个。
Yeah, with celebrities.
是的，和名人有关。
Yeah, you read about celebrities.
是的，你读到过关于名人的事。
So basically, a prenup is a short way of saying a prenuptial agreement.
所以基本上，prenup 是 prenuptial agreement 的简称。
Nuptial means having to do with marriage.
Nuptial 意思是与婚姻有关的。
Right.
对。
So basically, if you sign a prenup, you are agreeing to certain conditions before you
所以基本上，如果你签了婚前协议，你就是在同意某些条件，在你
get married.
结婚之前。
That's right.
没错。
It's a contract between future husband and future wife about what happens if they divorce.
这是未来丈夫和未来妻子之间关于离婚后会发生什么的合同。
For example, I decided not to get a prenup with my fiancé because I don't think we'll
例如，我决定不和我的未婚夫签婚前协议，因为我觉得我们不会
get divorced.
离婚。
But maybe he decided to get a prenup because in case they divorce, he wants to keep his
但也许他决定签婚前协议，以防他们离婚，他想保留他的
car.
车。
Right.
对。
So it usually happens a lot with celebrities, as we say, because they have a lot of money.
所以这通常发生在名人身上，就像我们说的，因为他们有很多钱。
And if they get divorced, then usually it can get complicated, how much money the spouse
如果他们离婚了，那么通常会很复杂，配偶能得到多少钱
gets, etc.
等等。
So maybe their prenuptial agreement or prenup will be that if they get divorced, the wife
所以他们的婚前协议可能会规定，如果他们离婚，妻子
may get maybe a million dollars instead of a hundred million dollars.
可能得到一百万美元，而不是一亿美元。
Exactly.
正是如此。
It's a way many people protect themselves financially in case of divorce.
这是很多人在离婚时保护自己财务的一种方式。
Very good.
非常好。
Now, moving on, another legal term and related to money is an alimony.
现在，我们继续，另一个与金钱相关的法律术语是赡养费。
Okay, so let's look at the context of this word.
好的，让我们看看这个词的语境。
Joanne is talking and she says, my lawyer tells me you've accepted our alimony proposal.
乔安妮在说话，她说：“我的律师告诉我，你已经接受了我们的赡养费提议。”
Alimony.
赡养费。
So this is probably something to do with money, right?
所以这很可能和钱有关，对吧？
So she said that her lawyer has proposed an alimony and that's usually a settlement, an
所以她说她的律师提出了一个赡养费方案，这通常是一种和解，一个
amount of money that you agree on when you get divorced.
你离婚时同意的金额。
Right.
对。
So this is exactly it.
所以就是这样。
In a divorce, this is how much money one person will pay the other.
在离婚中，这是一方支付给另一方的金额。
That's right.
没错。
So if two people are married and when they get a divorce, their alimony may be the husband.
所以如果两个人结婚了，当他们离婚时，他们的赡养费可能是丈夫
If he's got a lot of money, he will pay an alimony of $500,000.
如果他有很多钱，他会支付50万美元的赡养费。
Right.
对。
And so this is different from property, which is the next thing.
这和财产不同，财产是下一件事。
Division of property means that you talk about who will receive the car, the house, things
财产分割意味着你们讨论谁将得到车、房子之类的
like that.
东西。
Lands.
土地。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
So very complicated situations when you're getting divorced, the prenups and alimony.
所以离婚时情况非常复杂，涉及婚前协议和赡养费。
But moving on, they were talking about custody as well.
但继续，他们也在谈论监护权。
Custody of maybe children, maybe custody of their pets.
可能是孩子的监护权，也可能是宠物的监护权。
That's right.
没错。
So you talk about alimony, this is money, property, which is things.
所以你谈到赡养费，这是钱；财产，这是物品。
But what about people and animals?
但人和动物呢？
This is called custody.
这叫做监护权。
I want custody.
我想要监护权。
Custody means caring for something or looking after something.
监护权意味着照顾某物或照看某物。
You could say the child is in the grandmother's custody.
你可以说孩子由祖母监护。
Okay, so in the care of the grandmother.
好的，所以由祖母照顾。
That's right.
没错。
So usually as well, when people get divorced, somebody gets custody of the children.
所以通常，当人们离婚时，有人会获得孩子的监护权。
Right.
对。
So he wants custody, but he doesn't have a job, so she will receive custody.
所以他想要监护权，但他没有工作，所以她会得到监护权。
You could say that.
你可以这么说。
In this case, though, we're talking about custody of pets, animals.
但在这个案例中，我们谈论的是宠物、动物的监护权。
Right.
对。
In this case, it's animals.
在这个案例中，是动物。
But it's actually true, right?
但这确实是真的，对吧？
People when they get divorced, they may ask the court for custody of their pets.
人们离婚时，可能会向法院申请宠物的监护权。
That's right.
没错。
And sometimes custody is what makes a divorce extremely acrimonious.
有时监护权会让离婚变得极其充满敌意。
Yes.
是的。
Who gets to keep the children?
谁得到孩子？
Who gets to keep the pets?
谁得到宠物？
Now moving on and a little bit away from legal terms, they were dividing up their property
现在继续，稍微偏离法律术语，他们在分割他们的财产。
and saying, well, I get to keep this, you get to keep that.
然后说，好吧，这个归我，那个归你。
And Joanne said, I'm keeping the antique gramophone as my grandfather gave it to me.
乔安妮说，我要留着古董留声机，因为是我祖父给我的。
Ha, so who cares about pets and money?
哈，那谁还在乎宠物和钱啊？
I want the gramophone.
我要留声机。
Right.
对。
All right.
好吧。
So this is actually a word you don't hear very often anymore.
所以这其实是个现在不常听到的词了。
It's an old thing.
是个老物件。
And that's what antique means, right?
这就是“antique”的意思，对吧？
Antique is old.
“Antique”就是旧的。
Right.
对。
So antique, this is an adjective here.
所以“antique”在这里是形容词。
It can also be a noun.
它也可以是名词。
An antique table, an antique gramophone is something that's very old, like 100 years
一张古董桌子、一台古董留声机，就是非常老的东西，比如有100年
old or 150 years old.
或150年历史。
And a gramophone is one of those machines that you see in movies that play the old vinyl
留声机就是你在电影里看到的那种机器，播放老式黑胶唱片，
records and has like a big horn where the sound echoes.
还有一个大喇叭，声音在里面回荡。
That's right.
没错。
So in the 19th century, early 20th century, people didn't have CDs or MP3s or iPods.
所以在19世纪、20世纪初，人们没有CD、MP3或iPod。
This is how they listened to music.
他们就是这样听音乐的。
So you usually have a hand crank.
通常有个手摇曲柄。
You have to turn the machine and then the music will play and you can dance and do whatever.
你得转动机器，然后音乐就会播放，你可以跳舞或做别的。
Right.
对。
So that's a gramophone.
那就是留声机。
Now, moving on to our last word, Jeff said, you know what?
现在，说到最后一个词，杰夫说，你知道吗？
OK, fine.
好吧，行。
Keep the gramophone.
留声机你留着吧。
All right.
好吧。
I'll concede the silly gramophone.
我放弃那个破留声机。
So to concede.
所以“to concede”。
To concede means to give up an argument.
“To concede”意思是放弃争论。
OK, so you give up, you give in, you say, all right, take it.
对，就是你认输、让步，说，好吧，拿去吧。
That's exactly right.
完全正确。
So in this case, the argument is who will receive the gramophone?
所以在这个例子里，争论的是谁得到留声机？
They fight, they argue.
他们争吵、争论。
And finally, Jeff says, I concede.
最后杰夫说，我认输。
OK, I give up.
好吧，我放弃。
You take it.
你拿去吧。
And is it only for things or can you also concede someone, like you say somebody is
这个只用于东西吗？还是也可以用于人，比如你说某人
right?
是对的？
You can say that or in election, for example, there are two people who want to be president.
你可以这么说，或者比如在选举中，有两个人想当总统。
And the vote is counted and it's not clear who the president is.
计票后，谁当总统还不明确。
And one person says, fine, I concede.
然后一个人说，好吧，我认输。
That means I give up.
意思就是我放弃。
You win.
你赢了。
OK, very good.
好，非常好。
So to concede.
所以“to concede”。
All right.
好吧。
Six key words there.
这里有六个关键词。
They're very interesting, especially the legal terms.
它们很有趣，尤其是法律术语。
Very common.
很常见。
And it's very it's very common and it's very useful for you to know next time you're watching
而且很常见，对你下次看
maybe a movie or something related to this topic.
电影或相关话题很有用。
Hopefully not the next time you're getting divorced.
希望不是你下次离婚的时候。
But move let's move on now to four key phrases that we have for everyone on Fluency Builder.
但我们现在进入“Fluency Builder”的四个关键短语。
Fluency Builder.
“Fluency Builder”。
Margo, let's get this over with.
玛戈，我们快点搞定吧。
I'm tired.
我累了。
I want to go home.
我想回家。
Let's get it over with.
快点搞定吧。
Come on.
来吧。
Just do it and get it over with.
就去做，快点搞定。
All right.
好吧。
So this is our first phrase in Fluency Builder.
这是“Fluency Builder”里的第一个短语。
To get this over with or to get it over with.
“To get this over with”或“to get it over with”。
OK, so let's take that as a phrase.
好，我们就把它当作一个短语。
And to get something over with means this just finish it quickly.
“To get something over with”意思就是快点完成。
Let's stop delaying.
别再拖延了。
That's right.
没错。
This is a this is a way to ask to finish something quickly or to stop something.
这是一种要求快点完成某事或停止某事的方式。
So for example, I have to go to the dentist later.
比如，我待会儿得去看牙医。
Maybe I really don't want to go.
可能我真的很不想去。
I'll say to myself, oh, let me just get this over with.
我会对自己说，哦，让我快点搞定吧。
And once it's done, I don't have to worry about it.
一旦做完，我就不用担心了。
Or maybe you have homework to do.
或者你可能有作业要做。
And instead of doing it later, you're like, OK, I'm going to do it now and just get it
与其晚点做，不如说，好，我现在就做，快点
over with.
搞定。
All right.
好吧。
To get over with to get something over with.
“To get over with”、“to get something over with”。
OK.
好。
And when they were talking about breaking up or separating, Joanne mentioned it's important
当他们谈论分手或分开时，乔安妮提到，重要的是
we make a clean break.
我们要彻底断绝关系。
What does she mean by making a clean break?
她说的“彻底断绝关系”是什么意思？
All right.
好的。
We hear this phrase all the time.
我们经常听到这个短语。
It's a very important phrase in the relationships.
这是人际关系中一个非常重要的短语。
It means when two people leave each other, you don't then call them or see each other
它的意思是，当两个人分开后，你不会再打电话、见面
or hang out.
或一起出去玩。
It means a clean break.
这就是“彻底断绝关系”。
You stop all together.
你完全停止一切联系。
You stop something completely.
你完全停止某件事。
So you don't talk anymore.
所以你们不再交谈。
You don't see each other anymore.
你们不再见面。
You completely just stop contact with each other.
你们完全停止与对方联系。
Exactly.
没错。
You can also say this about breaking something.
你也可以用这个说法来形容东西断裂。
You could say it was a clean break.
你可以说它是“干净利落的断裂”。
When I broke my arm, it was a clean break.
当我摔断胳膊时，那是干净利落的骨折。
There were no little pieces of bone or any problems.
没有碎骨或任何问题。
It was a clean break.
那是干净利落的骨折。
That means completely broke.
意思是完全断裂。
OK.
好的。
So when we talk about clean break in a relationship, it means we completely break up.
所以当我们谈论人际关系中的“彻底断绝关系”时，意思是完全分手。
We stop talking to each other and it's over with.
我们停止交谈，一切都结束了。
It's in the past.
它已成为过去。
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好的。
So moving on, they were talking and completely, you know, arguing about I get the gramophone,
那么继续，他们当时在谈论，完全在争吵，比如“我拿留声机，
I get the tea set.
我拿茶具。”
And Joanne said, OK, fine.
然后乔安妮说：“好吧，行。”
I don't want to drag this out any longer than necessary.
“我不想再拖下去了，没必要。”
So you can hear her, I don't want to drag this out any longer than necessary.
所以你能听到她说：“我不想再拖下去了，没必要。”
So to drag something out means to extend, to make something longer, to make something
所以“拖下去”意思是延长，让某事变长，让某事
take more time than it should.
花费比必要更多的时间。
OK.
好的。
So, for example, if someone's giving a speech, they may be dragging it out.
所以，举个例子，如果有人发表演讲，他们可能是在拖时间。
Right.
对。
And you're like, wait.
然后你会想：“等等。”
So someone's giving a very long speech.
所以有人在发表一个很长的演讲。
You're like, oh, my God, he's dragging the speech out so long.
你会想：“天哪，他把演讲拖得太长了。”
Yeah.
是啊。
When will he ever stop?
“他什么时候才能停下来？”
Right.
对。
Or you could say in an argument, I'm tired of arguing.
或者你可以在争吵中说：“我吵累了。”
Let's not drag this out anymore.
“我们别再拖下去了。”
Let's just stop.
“我们就此打住吧。”
OK.
好的。
So to drag something out is usually time related to make things longer than necessary.
所以“拖下去”通常与时间有关，意思是让事情比必要的时间更长。
Exactly.
没错。
All right.
好的。
And for our last phrase, when Jeff was talking about the relationship, he says, I know a
至于我们最后一个短语，当杰夫谈论这段关系时，他说：“我知道一段
relationship has been on the rocks for some time.
关系已经‘触礁’一段时间了。”
OK.
好的。
So the relationship was on the rocks.
所以这段关系“触礁”了。
OK.
好的。
So this is an interesting phrase.
所以这是一个有趣的短语。
Think about rocks.
想想岩石。
You know, you see rocks on the ground in the ocean.
你知道，你会看到地上或海里的岩石。
Something that's on the rocks, in this case, means something that is not going well.
“触礁”在这种情况下，意思是某事进展不顺利。
Something that has problems.
某事有问题。
Not going smooth.
不顺利。
Yes, it's not smooth.
是的，不顺利。
So, when Jeff says our relationship has been on the rocks, he's saying we fight a lot.
所以，当杰夫说我们的关系“触礁”时，他是在说我们经常吵架。
We have problems.
我们有问题。
It's not working.
关系不顺利。
So, if I say, my company has been on the rocks recently, it means it's not doing very well.
所以，如果我说我的公司最近“触礁”了，意思是它经营得不太好。
Business is not going well.
生意不顺利。
OK.
好的。
So, you can use this for different things.
所以，你可以用这个说法来形容不同的事情。
Now, obviously, you may have heard it before for drinks.
现在，显然，你可能以前听过它用于饮料。
You say, scotch on the rocks.
你说：“加冰的苏格兰威士忌。”
Right.
对。
That's different.
那是不同的意思。
Be careful.
小心。
In that sentence, Marco's talking about ice.
在那个句子里，马可说的是冰块。
Right.
对。
Yeah.
是啊。
So, that's different if you ask for a drink on the rocks.
所以，如果你点一杯“加冰的饮料”，那是不同的意思。
But if you describe yourself or your company or relationship as being on the rocks, it
但如果你形容自己、公司或关系“触礁”，
means you're having a tough time.
意思是你在经历一段艰难时期。
It's a bad situation.
情况不妙。
Exactly.
没错。
So, it's a very useful phrase.
所以，这是一个非常有用的短语。
I think that's very native, very colloquial if you say something like this.
我觉得如果你这样说，听起来非常地道、非常口语化。
Absolutely.
绝对。
It's a great phrase to use.
这是一个很棒的短语。
I encourage you.
我鼓励你。
I mean, I hope that your situation, your work and your relationships are not on the rocks.
我是说，我希望你的处境、工作和感情关系没有出现问题。
But I do hope that when you're practicing speaking, use this phrase a lot because it's
但我确实希望你在练习口语时，多使用这个短语，因为它
really, really colloquial like you say, Marco.
非常非常口语化，就像你说的，Marco。
Yeah.
嗯。
It's really good.
真的很好。
So, I think we've taken a look at a lot of phrases, a lot of vocab.
所以，我想我们已经看了很多短语和词汇。
Why don't we go back, listen to the dialogue for one last time.
我们不如回去，再听一遍对话吧。
What was that?
那是什么？
Exactly.
没错。
Madam please.
女士，请。
disco albums back. Fine, but I'm keeping the antique gramophone as my grandfather
迪斯科专辑可以拿走。好吧，但我留着古董留声机，因为是我祖父
gave it to me. I believe that was a wedding present to both of us Joanne and
给我的。我相信那是送给Joanne和我的结婚礼物，
you hardly ever use it. He's my grandfather and he never really liked
你几乎从来不用它。他是我祖父，而且他从来都不怎么喜欢
you anyway. Whatever! Alright I'll concede this silly gramophone if you agree that
你。随便吧！好吧，我放弃这个傻留声机，如果你同意
I get the silver tea set. How typical, when are you ever going to use a silver
我拿银茶具。真典型，你什么时候会用银
tea set? Fine, I don't want to drag this out any more than necessary.
茶具？好吧，我不想再拖下去了。
What's next? What about these old photographs? Which ones? Let me have a
接下来呢？这些老照片怎么办？哪些？让我看看。
look. Oh wow look at that, that brings back memories. Remember that? Our trip to
哦，哇，看这个，这勾起了回忆。还记得吗？我们去
Italy, I remember that day. We were going to visit the Trevi Fountain and we got
意大利的旅行，我记得那天。我们本来要去参观特雷维喷泉，结果
caught in the rain. And you looked so adorable with your hair all wet. I did
遇上了雨。你头发全湿的样子太可爱了。我确实
take a picture of you standing there in that little alley smiling and laughing
给你拍了张照片，你站在那个小巷子里，在雨中微笑大笑。
in the rain. Oh we really did have fun back then didn't we? Oh Joanne, are we
哦，我们那时候真的玩得很开心，不是吗？哦，Joanne，我们
making a big mistake? I know our relationship has been on the rocks for
是不是犯了个大错？我知道我们的关系已经紧张
some time, but are you sure we can't reconcile and try again? I still love
一段时间了，但你确定我们不能和解再试一次吗？我还爱
you. Oh Jeff, I love you too. I'm so glad we didn't have to decide who keeps the
你。哦，Jeff，我也爱你。真高兴我们不用决定谁留着那辆
motorcycle. The motorcycle? But that's mine!
摩托车。摩托车？那是我的！
Alright we're back. So a very interesting dialogue all about divorce. Now this is a
好了，我们回来了。一个非常有趣的对话，全是关于离婚的。现在这在
very common situation nowadays in many countries such as the United States or
很多国家都很常见，比如美国或
Europe. Divorce rates are very high lately like in the past 10-20 years. Yeah
欧洲。最近离婚率很高，比如过去10-20年。是啊，
they do say that since maybe the 70s or 80s divorce rates have been on the rise.
他们确实说，大概从70年代或80年代开始，离婚率一直在上升。
I think the average now in America is about 50%. Yeah it's like 5 in 10
我觉得现在美国的平均离婚率大约是50%。是啊，差不多每10对
marriages and in divorce. That's right. And then from what I understand or I
婚姻中有5对离婚。没错。而且据我所知，或者我
read once, I think out of those 50% that get divorced, if they remarry again the
曾经读到过，我想在那50%离婚的人中，如果他们再婚，
probabilities of those that get remarried are again half. So most likely
再婚的人离婚的概率又是半数。所以很可能
people will get divorced at least twice. That's true. Although sometimes you meet
人们至少会离婚两次。确实如此。虽然有时你会遇到
people who got married when they were very very young and they realized that
那些非常年轻就结婚的人，他们后来意识到
they grew up a little bit and their personality changed or their goals
自己长大了一点，性格变了，或者目标
changed and they divorced that one time but then later in life when they marry
变了，于是离婚了一次，但后来在生活中再婚时，
again they know who they are. They get married again and it's better. So I think
他们了解了自己。他们再婚，结果更好。所以我认为
the situations are all quite different but it is true that there are a lot of a
情况各不相同，但确实在美国有很多很多
lot of divorces in America. What about Ecuador though? I mean is the divorce
离婚。那厄瓜多尔呢？我是说，离婚率
rate similar? No not really. I think people are still a little bit more
类似吗？不，不太一样。我觉得人们在这方面还是有点
old-fashioned in that sense like it was before you know it was even a little bit
守旧，就像以前一样，离婚甚至有点
taboo to be divorced. Yeah. But I don't think people get divorced as often
禁忌。嗯。但我不认为人们经常离婚，
especially if people have been together for quite a while. That's one of the
尤其是如果两个人在一起很久了。这让我很
things that surprises me a lot is I've met people who have been married 20-30
惊讶的一点是，我遇到过结婚20-30年
years and then get divorced. It's like what if it's like you've been through
然后离婚的人。这就像，你们已经经历了
the toughest times you know you've pretty much beat the odds and why do you
最艰难的时期，基本上已经战胜了困难，为什么还要
get divorced at such a late age? Yeah it does seem counterintuitive but it's
在这么晚的年纪离婚？是啊，这似乎违反直觉，但
possible that they were unhappy for that time and they didn't want to affect
有可能他们在那段时间一直不快乐，不想影响
their children's lives. Right. So when their children go to college or leave
孩子的生活。对。所以当孩子上大学或离开家时，
they say okay now I can I can you know make a big decision. I know in countries
他们就说，好了，现在我可以做出重大决定了。我知道在一些国家，
for example such as Chile divorce is still illegal. I think in the Philippines
比如智利，离婚仍然是非法的。我想菲律宾
as well. Really? Yeah it's still illegal to get divorced. Is that because they're
也是。真的吗？是啊，离婚仍然是非法的。是因为他们是
very religious countries? I know Chile is not really that religious. I don't
非常宗教化的国家吗？我知道智利并没有那么宗教化。我不
know what it is exactly by law but a lot of people I think it may be legal now I
知道法律具体怎么规定，但很多人，我想现在可能合法了，我
can't really remember very well I think one of our Chilean listeners can help
记不太清了，我想我们的一位智利听众可以帮我们
us out here but I know a lot of people used to annul their marriages because of
解答，但我知道很多人过去因此宣布婚姻无效。
this. I see. So they would be like oh I put the wrong address so no this marriage
我明白了。所以他们会说，哦，我填错了地址，所以这段婚姻
is not it's not valid. Right or I spelled my name wrong. Yeah yeah. Interesting. Well I'd be
无效。对，或者我拼错了名字。是啊是啊。有意思。好吧，我
curious to know as you said whether any of our Chilean friends know more about
很好奇，就像你说的，我们的智利朋友是否了解更多
this or for the rest of you in your country is divorce common? Is it
这方面的情况，或者对于你们其他人来说，在你们国家离婚常见吗？
uncommon? Are there laws that prohibit or that allow divorce? Let us know on our
不常见吗？有没有禁止或允许离婚的法律？在我们的
website EnglishPod.com. Alright we'll see you guys there. Bye.
网站EnglishPod.com上告诉我们。好了，我们那里见。再见。